Guide to the Riker family papers 1985.003
Brooklyn Historical Society
Riker family papers
1869-1950
Brooklyn Historical Society
Smith, Michael M.
Riker family
1985.003
14 Linear Feet in twenty two manuscript boxes, four ledgers, and one oversize folder
This collection contains the financial records of the Riker family, dating from 1869 to 1950. Family members documented in the collection include John L. Riker, John J. Riker, Charles L. Riker, Henry L. Riker, Mary J. Riker, Edith B. Riker, Margaret Riker Haskell, Selina Schroeder Riker, and Lavinia R. Strong. Materials in the collection include account books, receipts, correspondence, real estate records, estate records, and tax records. It also includes photographic negatives relating to estate at Sea Bright, New Jersey (1936-1944), photographic prints of the Riker family homestead, mezzotint portraits of John L. Riker and an unidentified man (circa 1880s), flyers detailing the like of John Jackson Riker from the Co-Operative Press (October 26, 1910), and maps of Westchester County property.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the financial records of the Riker family, dating from 1869 to 1950. Family members documented in the collection include John L. Riker, John J. Riker, Charles L. Riker, Henry L. Riker, Mary J. Riker, Edith B. Riker, Margaret Riker Haskell, Selina Schroeder Riker, and Lavinia R. Strong. Materials in the collection include account books, receipts, correspondence, real estate records, estate records, and tax records. It also includes photographic negatives relating to estate at Sea Bright, New Jersey (1936-1944), photographic prints of the Riker family homestead, mezzotint portraits of John L. Riker and an unidentified man (circa 1880s), flyers detailing the like of John Jackson Riker from the Co-Operative Press (October 26, 1910), and maps of Westchester County property.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Michael M. Smith, 1985.
Biographical note
The Riker family ancestry extends back to the early Dutch settlers of New York, specifically to the von Rycken family of Amsterdam, where several members of the von Rycken family were successful in establishing Dutch independence alongside William I, Prince of Orange in the Dutch Revolt. The first American settler of the Rycken family was Abraham Rycken, who settled in New Netherland in 1636. Later in 1654, Abraham would acquire a land in the Township of Newtown in present day Queens County. On this land, the Riker family established the Riker Homestead and burial ground.
John Lawrence Riker (1830-1909) was a prominent New York City merchant, best known as the founder of J.L. & D.S. Riker, a drug and chemical trading firm. He married Mary Anne Jackson in 1857. His first son, John Jackson Riker, was born in 1858 and became a partner in his father's firm in 1888. On April 20, 1881, John Jackson married Edith M. Bartow in Brooklyn, New York. In December of 1901, John Jackson Riker was elected president of the newly incorporated J. L. & D. S. Riker, Inc. John J. Riker held many other leadership positions including director of the Farmers' Loan & Trust Company and incorporator and director of the Mutual Trust Company in Westchester County, New York. He died in 1932.
Arrangement
The collection is unorganized.
Related Materials
The Brooklyn, N.Y., Department of Law, Corporation Counsel records (2013.015) contains two files relating to Long Island City property assessment disputes filed by the Riker family in 1897 (Box: 101, Folders: 2-3).
The BHS library holds books related to the Riker family, including:
Alig, Mary Ryker. Rycken-Riker-Ryker and allied families. Kansas City, Mo.: M.R. Alig, 1982. (Main Collection CS71 .R535 1982)
Riker, James. The annals of Newtown, in Queens county, New-York: containing its history from its first settlement, together with many interesting facts concerning the adjacent towns; also, a particular account of numerous Long island families now spread over this and various other states of the union. New-York: D. Fanshaw, 1852. (Main Collection F127.Q3 R5 1852)
Riker, James. A brief history of the Riker family: from their first emigration to this country in the year 1638, to the present time. New-York: D. Fanshaw, 1851. (Main Collection CS71 .R535 1851)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Newtown (Queens County, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Decedents' estates |z New York (State); Portraits; Account books; Sea Bright (N.J.); Westchester County (N.Y.); Decedents' estates |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Maps; Negatives (photographic); Photographs; Correspondence; Tax records; Estate records; Financial records; Receipts (financial records); Carborundum mezzotints (prints); Ledgers (account books); Chemical industry |z New York (State) |z New York; Pharmaceutical industry |z New York (State) |z New York; Riker family; Smith, Michael M.; Riker, John J.; Riker, John L.
- Box of file folders and papers of bill of estate of Henry L. Riker, tax and water bills (1892-1904), individual tax returns of Edith Riker (1917-1923) and correspondence about trust (1934), pay stubs of John H. Stell's monthly wages, tax documents, insurance policies, clippings, and negatives relating to estate at Sea Bright, NJ (1936-1944), receipts from executors of John L. Riker's estate (1930-1932), yearly expenditures (1893-1939), documents relating to Trains Meadow Property (1941-1945), and documents relating to Selina Schroeder Riker's death (1939-1944), four account ledgers relating to the estate of John L. Riker (1910-1946), 1892-1946 (Box 1 of 22)
- Tax receipts of estate (1919), receipts of cash and stock distribution (1938-1940), and one account ledger (1922-1928), 1919-1940 (Box 2 of 22)
- Four account ledgers, 1905-1929 (Box 3 of 22)
- Five account ledgers (1908-1948), stack of receipts of services (1950), four property leases (1936-1939), and bank receipts (1945-1947), 1908-1950 (Box 4 of 22)
- Two black leather ledgers (1914-1919), copies of the last will and testement of John L. Riker (1901), and two small tan leather account ledgers from Bank of New York (1942-1948), 1901-1948 (Box 5 of 22)
- Account balances of John J. Riker (1930-1931) and tax receipts of Mary J. Riker (1913 and 1917), 1913-1931 (Box 6 of 22)
- Tax receipts for the years 1912 and 1922, 1912-1922 (Box 7 of 22)
- Ledger of real estate accounts from the estate of John L. Riker (1942-1948) and two black leather binder ledgers (1909-1914), 1909-1948 (Box 8 of 22)
- Tax receipts of Mary J. Riker (1915) and one account ledger (1876-1907), 1876-1915 (Box 9 of 22)
- Small acount book from Lavinia R. Strong (1921-1933), stack of bill of real estate from Mary J. Riker (1924-1925), and bills for water and real estate taxes (1903-1918), 1903-1933 (Box 10 of 22)
- Estate of John L. Riker tax reciepts (1917-1922) and tax receipts of 1918 (Box 11 of 22)
- Documents relating to the estates of John J. Riker and Edith B. Riker (1912-1943), Mary J. Riker bill of property (1903), and income tax returns (1929-1945), 1903-1945 (Box 12 of 22)
- Financial documents (1930-1937), tax receipts and receipted tax bills (1915-1916), maps of Westchester County property, and Estate of Mary J. Riker tax reciepts (1910-1911), 1910-1937 (Box 13 of 22)
- The Commercial and Financial Chronical (1869 June 12), American Rail Road Journal (1869 May 15), Riker Homestead Estates receipted tax bills (1915-1916), and bill for real estate (1921-1923), 1869-1923 (Box 14 of 22)
- Correspondence regarding hopeful future endowement of fellowship to honor the late John J. Riker (1933), listing of estate of John L. Riker, tax receipt of John L. Riker (1908-1915), and income tax returns (1928-1943), 1908-1943 (Box 15 of 22)
- Stack of flyers detailing the like of John Jackson Riker from the Co-Operative Press (October 26, 1910), financial documents (1934-1950), tax receipts (1920), and Federal NYS tax forms (1923-1926), 1910-1950 (Box 16 of 22)
- Estate of Mary J. Riker tax assesments (1904-1926), documents relating to Riker estate (1920-1944), trust agreements (1902), financial literature (1921), and prints of Riker family homestead, 1902-1944 (Box 17 of 22)
- Legal documents (1934); documents relating to the Monmouth Beach Property (1933-1946), Trust of Charles L. Riker (1930-1937), and No. 43 Fulton Street (1929-1946); tax documents of Riker estate (1907-1919); tax documents of Estate of Mary J. Riker (1903-1909); tax literature (1929); documents relating to Knowllwood Cemetry (1901-1947); documents relating to First Lake Realty Corp. (1922-1923); Federal and State income tax returns (1917-1921); and tax documents of Mary J. Riker (1896-1898), 1896-1947 (Box 18 of 22)
- Taxes from Mary J. Riker (1899-1905), documents relating to Margaret Riker Haskwell (1930-1942), 72 Front Street property (1903 to 1943), tax receipts (1930-1936), taxes of estate of Mary J. Riker (1907-1909), and documents relating to East 57th Street (1943-1947), 1899-1947 (Box 19 of 22)
- Bill for 1st and 2nd payement real estate taxes 1913 and 1916, 1923 to 1929, 1913-1929 (Box 20 of 22)
- Tax forms and schedules (1909-1920) and stack of real estate account receipts (1935-1941), 1909-1941 (Box 21 of 22)
- One black leather ledger of checks (1929-1934), tax receipts of JLR (1897-1912), tax bills of JLR (1910), bank receipts of JLR (1929-1931), loss of stocks and bonds (1909-1913), documents relating to Riker Homestead Estates (1918-1932), East 57th St and Sea Bright property (1939-1943), lease document (1904-1942), Chesterdonack Realty Inc. (1938-1946), taxes of MJR (1917), and receipts of account of administrators of will of MJR (1937-1939), 1897-1946 (Box 22 of 22)
- Financial ledger, 1903-1913 (Item Ledger 1 of 4)
- Financial ledger, 1908 (Item Ledger 2 of 4)
- Financial ledger, 1918-1927 (Item Ledger 3 of 4)
- Financial ledger, 1923-1927 (Item Ledger 4 of 4)
- Mezzotint portraits of John L. Riker and an unidentified man, circa 1880s (Oversize OS-4)